<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A new boke of the natures and properties of all wines that are commonly vsed here in England with a confutation of an errour of some men, that holde, that Rhennish and other small white wines ought not to be drunken of them that either haue, or are in daunger of the stone, the revine, and diuers other diseases, made by William Turner, doctor of Phisicke. Whereunto is annexed the booke of the natures and vertues of triacles, newly corrected and set foorth againe by the sayde William Turner.</title>
            <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1568</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 105 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24360</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103034</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838793</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838793</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3182</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14053)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3182)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1158:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A new boke of the natures and properties of all wines that are commonly vsed here in England with a confutation of an errour of some men, that holde, that Rhennish and other small white wines ought not to be drunken of them that either haue, or are in daunger of the stone, the revine, and diuers other diseases, made by William Turner, doctor of Phisicke. Whereunto is annexed the booke of the natures and vertues of triacles, newly corrected and set foorth againe by the sayde William Turner.</title>
                  <author>Turner, William, d. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[96] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By William Seres,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1568.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>This section on "triacles" has a divisional title page, which reads: This booke sheweth at large the pwers, commodities, vertues, and properties of the three most renouned and famous preseruatives or triacles .. Gather'd out of Galen, and Aëtius, by .. William Turner, ..</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-F G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wine and wine making --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Antidotes --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A new Boke of the natures and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of all Wines that are commonlye vſed here in England, with a confutation of an errour of ſome men, that holde, that Rhenniſh and other ſmall white wines ought not to be drunken of them that either haue, or are in daunger of the ſtone, the reume, and diuers other diſeaſes, made by Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Turner, doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke.</p>
                  <p>Whervnto is annexed the booke of the natures and vertues of Triacles, newly correc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſet foorth againe by the ſayde William Turner.</p>
                  <p>Jmprinted at London, by William Seres. Anno. 1568.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:2"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>TO THE RIGHT honorable Sir William</hi> Cecill Knight, chiefe Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie <hi>vnto the Queenes Maieſtye, and</hi> maiſter of hir Highneſſe Courts of Wardes and Liueries. &amp;c. and ſomtime his Conſtudent in the Vniuerſitie of Cambridge, William Turner wiſheth all proſperitie both of bodye and ſoule, through Ieſus Christ our Sauiour.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, AFTER that I perceiued that my age ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſickeneſſe, would ſuffer me no more to be profytable too Chriſtes Church and common welth, by my voyce, wordes, and going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode, thought it meete by ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and meanes as GOD hath left in
<pb facs="tcp:3182:3"/> me as yet vnhurt and vntouched, for that portion of liuing that I haue, to profit the Church of God as much as I coulde. And therefore within theſe xij. Monethes I haue tranſlated one booke out of Latin into Engliſh, and haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one homily againſt Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonye and Drunkenneſſe, and other vices annexed thervnto, and haue ſet them abrode, for the promoting and increaſing of the kingdome of GOD. I thought alſo, ſeeing that God hath alſo endued mee with the knowledge of bodilye Phiſicke, after that I had ſought to promote the kingdome of GOD, to communicate ſome part of my knowledge that God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto me in naturall knowledge, vnto my brethren that had nede ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. But when as I perceiued that there was ſo much vſe of Wine in all cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tries of Englande, and ſo many errors committed in the abuſing of it, both of the moſt part of the Laitie, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo of ſome of the learned that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3182:3"/> naturall knowledge, I thought I ſhould doe no ſmall benefite vnto the Church and Common welth of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, if that I ſhoulde ſet out a booke of the natures of Wines, and confute the errors and ill opinions that all men haue concerning the natures and properties of them. And this booke haue I now ended, and dedicate vnto your Honor for a token of the good will that I beare vnto you, deſiring you alſo to be a Patrone of it againſt all ſuch babling and vnlearned So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſters, as wyll ſpeake agaynſt it, not being armed with learning, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and reaſon, but onelye with their olde Sophiſtrie, which they learned in the time of ignoraunce and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. If theſe will be to buſie in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending of their errors, and will goe about to defende them, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute the truth that I haue taught in this booke, if that I can haue by the helpe of God, graunted vnto me any truce betweene me and my diſeaſe, I
<pb facs="tcp:3182:4"/> entende to put you to ſmall paine in the defending of my Booke, for I haue beene matched with as big men as theſe bee, I thanke GOD, and well haue eſcaped without diſhonor. But if my ſickneſſe will not ſuffer me to doe it that I would otherwiſe doe, then I muſt deſire you and other of my friendes to defende mee ſo farre forth as I defende the truth.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, whereas I ſet out of late a boke, declaring at large the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and properties of the great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle called <hi>Theriaca Andromachi,</hi> and of the Triacle of <hi>Mithridates</hi> called <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridatium,</hi> and alſo of the <hi>Triacle Salt,</hi> and the booke was negligentlye and falſelye printed, and diuerſe honeſt men think it neceſſarie to be printed againe, &amp; I purpoſe to doe the ſame, &amp; bicauſe it were neceſſary to haue a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone for it, which it hath wanted hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto: I dedicate and giue this boke alſo vnto your learned Honor, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you alſo by your learnyng and
<pb facs="tcp:3182:4"/> wiſedome to be patrone vnto it as I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aue made you of my other booke. No more at this time, but the Lorde Ieſus encreaſe you with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his holy worde, and with grace to lyue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes according to the ſame, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:5"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:5"/>
                  <head>OF THE NATVRES, properties, profits, hurtes and helps that come of Wyne.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGH the order of learning do require, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye man that ſhall write of anye thing, ſhould declare &amp; open by definitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it that he entendeth to entreate of: yet nede not I (as I iudge) going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to write of wine, to take any great paine to make a definition of it, bicauſe all men, women and childer, that are cummed to any perfite age, know well inough that Wine is the iuice of grapes preſſed out, and put vp into veſſels, to be drunken afterwards at co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient times of men, for diuerſe endes and purpoſes that the Grape maker hath ordeyned it for. For manye great cauſes, it ſhall be more neceſſarye to diuide Wine into his kindes and ſortes, that thereby the
<pb facs="tcp:3182:6"/> reader may the better know what kinds of Wines are beſt for what endes and purpoſes.<note place="margin">Wines may be diuided into ſixe ſorts at the least.</note> Wines may be numbred and diuided either by the countrie and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that they grow in, or by their colors, or by their youth, or age, and by their taſtes, ſmelles, and by properties that they haue, and ſome of the maner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and euery one of theſe kindes, may bee diuided againe into certaine other ſpeciall ſortes or vnder kindes.</p>
                  <p>Some Wine is called <hi>Creticum</hi> of <hi>Creta,</hi> which is named in Engliſh <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die,</hi> ſome is called <hi>Graecum</hi> of <hi>Graecia,</hi> ſome <hi>Rhenniſh,</hi> bicauſe it groweth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the <hi>Rhene,</hi> ſome <hi>Gallicum,</hi> that is French Wine, bicauſe it groweth in France, and ſome is called <hi>Rheticum</hi> bicauſe it groweth in <hi>Rhetia,</hi> and ſo a greate ſorte of other Wines haue their names of the countries, &amp; places wheras they growe. But it is beſt as I thinke, firſt of all according to nature to intreat of new and olde Wines, and of it that is a middle Wine betwene them both.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:3182:6"/>
                     <head>Of new and olde Wine, and of it that is of a meane age that is neyther to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led new nor olde.</head>
                     <p>THere are twoo ſortes of newe Wine, one that is called <hi>Muſt,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Two kindes of newe wine.</note> and that is but latelye made or preſſed out of the grapes, and is ſwete in taſt, troubled in color, and thick in ſubſtaunce, and this ſort is properlye called in Latin <hi>Muſtum.</hi> And another ſorte is called newe Wine, which hath left his ſwéetnes &amp; gotten cleareneſſe,<note place="margin">Galene.</note> but yet it is not long ſince it was made.<note place="margin">New wine after Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len.</note> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len in his booke of making of medicines, ſéemeth to call all Wine that is not fully fiue yeares olde, newe wine, and it that is paſt fiue yeares vntill it hee ten yeare olde, wine of middle age, and it that is aboue the age of ten yeares, olde wine, and <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> writing of the nature of Wines in his fifte booke, calleth it Wine of middle age, that is more than ſeauen yeare olde, and <hi>Plinie</hi> writeth,
<pb facs="tcp:3182:7"/> not without an error of the ſcribe (as I geſſe) that <hi>Falerno media aetas incipit ab anno decimo quinto.</hi> But <hi>Valerio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> a man otherwiſe wel learned,<note place="margin">Valeriola leaueth the authoritie of Galen.</note> leauing the authoritie of <hi>Galen,</hi> calleth it newe Wine that kéepeth ſtill his Muſtiſh and ſweete taſte, and as yet hath gotten no ſharpeneſſe, and he calleth that Wine of middle age, that is no more ſwéete, but is cleare, and ſayth that he and his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimen take the moſt notable Wines of Fraunce for olde Wines, before they bée fullye one yeare olde. And this doth he holde <hi>enarrationum medicinalium, lib. ſexto, enarratione ſeptima.</hi> In the ſame place he reproueth <hi>Aloiſius Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>della</hi> for ſaying that wine ſixe yeares olde was newe wine after <hi>Galen,</hi> who although fayled in excéeding one yeare beyond <hi>Galens</hi> numbring of the yeares of new wine, yet he went a great deale farther from <hi>Galens</hi> minde than <hi>Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>della</hi> did.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Muſt</hi> only hote in the firſt degree</note> 
                        <hi>Muſt</hi> when it is made euen of ripe grapes, is but hote in the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grée. for <hi>Galen</hi> in his boke of the powers of ſimple medicines, hath theſe wordes
<pb facs="tcp:3182:7"/> following. <hi>Vinum eſt ex fecundo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine excalfacientrum. Sed quod ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum vetus eſt ex tertio, ſicut quod muſtum vocant ex primo, caliditatis eius proportioni reſpondet ſiccitas,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Very olde wine hote in the third degree.</note> wine (that is to ſay of midle age) is hote in the ſeconde degrée, but it that is verie olde is hote in the third degree, as it that is called <hi>Muſt</hi> is hote in the firſt degrée. By theſe words their errour is openly confuted,<note place="margin">Non omne vinum eſſe calidum in ſecundo gradu.</note> that holde that euery wine is hote in the ſecond degrée. <hi>Galen</hi> writeth truly that the Grapes that grow in verie colde places, neuer come to ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, neither to ſwéeteneſſe, but when other wines are made, they are ſwéete &amp; pleaſant, but ſuch Wines made of ſuch grapes, are very ſoure and therfore colde, the words of <hi>Galen</hi> are theſe written in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond booke <hi>de alimentoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus. In regionibus frigidis ne vuae qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ipſae exquiſite maturari queunt, nedum paſſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaepiam, ob id quòd reſinam vinis immittant, ne aceſcant celeriter.</hi> That is. In colde countries neither raſins come to anye perfite ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3182:8"/> neither the grapes,<note place="margin">Roſin pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth ſmall wine from ſouring.</note> and therefore men put roſin into the wines, that they ſhoulde not ſhortly waxe ſoure. And in the booke of good and ill iuice he ſayth thus. The Wines that are to olde or to newe, are to be eſchued. For the olde doe heate to much, and the new Wines as long as they are greene,<note place="margin">Verie grene and new wines heate nothing at all.</note> or very new, heat nothing at all, ſo farre are they fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> helping of men to digeſt their meates, that they are very hardly digeſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and oft times they hang and abide ſtill in a mans ſtomacke, euen as water. <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> alſo who wrote before <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi> ſayth <hi>lib.</hi> 5. The ſinewes are hurte with olde wine, and other inſtruments of the ſenſes: yet for all that it is ſwéeter in taſte than the other wines are. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a man ought to beware of it, that feeleth the weakeneſſe of anye inwarde part. Yet when a man is in good helth a little being delayed with water, it maye be taken without harme. Newe Wine putteth a man vp,<note place="margin">New wine.</note> and filleth him with winde, and is hard of digeſtion and brée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth heauie dreames, and maketh a man
<pb facs="tcp:3182:8"/> to make water. It that is of a meane age betwéene both, is free from the harmes that maye come of both, wherefore it is commonlye vſed both of hole and ſicke men with their meate. <hi>Ariſtotel</hi> in his fourth booke <hi>Meteorologicorum</hi> the .x.<note place="margin">Newe wine hath much earthlyneſſe in it, and therfore ill for them that are dispoſed to the ſtone.</note> Chapter writeth. That new Wine hath more earth or earthlyneſſe in it than olde hath, wherevpon a man maye gather plainlye that new Wine is verye ill for them that are diſpoſed to the ſtone, for it hauing ſo much thicke earthlineſſe in it, giueth matter whereof the ſtone may be made to hote kidneys, that the heate of kidneis may ſo bake it into ſtones as the heate of the Bricke kill turneth the claye into Bricke or tile ſtones. Wherefore I muſt néedes diſpraiſe the maner of our delicate Engliſhmen and women that drinke the Rhenniſh wine only for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, whilſt it is as yet as thicke as pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or horſepiſſe. For beſide that it giueth matter to make the ſtone of, I haue kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen thrée within the ſpace of one yere in high Germany that toke the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by drinking much newe Rheniſhe
<pb facs="tcp:3182:9"/> wine, and they died all thrée, and coulde not be holpen with phiſicke, one of them ſodenly loſt his ſpech and died within an houre after that he ſickened, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two liued but a day or two after, and died miſerably with great paine, and had grieuous fittes of the falling ſickneſſe at ſundry times. I haue marked that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe doſen yeares there haue bene more ſicke in the falling ſickneſſe, than had wont to be before. The cauſe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I iudge to be, that mens wiues, nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,<note place="margin">The cauſes of the rife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the falling ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe nowe in England</note> and children drinke more Rhenniſhe <hi>Muſt,</hi> and other ſwéete wines vnfined, brought out alſo of other cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries as wel as out of Germany: tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were wont to drinke before in times paſt. <hi>Aetius</hi> a diligent follower of <hi>Galen,</hi> and a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full gatherer of the writinges of olde Greke writers of phiſick, ſaith that wine (meaning thereby wine of middle age that is neither verie new, neither verye olde) is hote in the ſecond degrée,<note place="margin">The degrees of wines by their ages.</note> and that verye olde is hote in the thirde degrée, as very new <hi>Muſt</hi> is hote in the firſt degrée. Ye maye ſée here once againe, that they
<pb facs="tcp:3182:9"/> are more bolde than learned and wiſe,<note place="margin">Whether al kindes of newe wines ought to bee refuſed or no?</note> that holde that all Wines are hote in the ſecond degrée. Some peraduenture will aſke whether there is any kinde of newe Wine that may ſerue for anye vſes, and may be dronken at any time or no<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To whom I make this aunſwere by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of <hi>Galen</hi> in his booke of good and euill iuice,<note place="margin">Si vina te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuia, alba &amp; aquoſae tutò bibi poſsint, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat Plinius qui vina tenuia &amp; auſtera magis ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put tentare aſſeuerat. lib. <hi>23.</hi> cap. <hi>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi>
                        </note> that <hi>ex recentibus vinis ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus illud du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taxat tutò bibitur, quod tenuis ſubſtantiae eſt, ſicuti ex Italicis Cauchanum &amp; Albanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c. quae ſanc tenuia, candida &amp; aquoſa exiſtunt. &amp;c</hi> That is. Amongſt new wines only that kinde maye be ſafelye drunken, that is of a thin ſubſtaunce, as amongſt Italian wines are <hi>Cauchanum</hi> &amp; <hi>Albanum.</hi> &amp;c. which wines in dede are thin, white, and wateriſh, and therfore are called <hi>Oligo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phora,</hi> that is, wines that can abide but ſmall menging of water with them.<note place="margin">Fulua vinae quia calida ſunt, caput cito replent, non igitur vini tenui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, ſed ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liditas ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put tentat.</note> And as rediſhe yelow Wines bicauſe they are hote in working, they fill the head by and by, ſo the other wines that are thin and wateriſh wines, and gently binding are not only not noyſome vnto the head, but
<pb facs="tcp:3182:10"/> oft times take awaye light head aches which come of humors gathered togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſtomache,<note place="margin">Hic Gale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Pliniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; eius diſcipulos manifeſte impugnat.</note> thus farre <hi>Galen.</hi> Nowe ſome men that reade this booke, acknowledging the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be my ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture would learne of me bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I teach Engliſh men in this Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh booke, what kindes of wines that are brought into England,<note place="margin">Smal wines helps the hedache, but make it not.</note> are of this ſort. I anſwere, that neither Sacke, Malmeſey, Muſcadell, neither Clared, French nor Gaſcone wine, though they be moſt vſed here in Englande at this time, are ſuch Wines as <hi>Galen</hi> ſpeaketh of here, but Rhenniſh wine that is racket and cleare, and Rochell, and Sebes and other ſmall white Wines that are cleare from their groundes, therefore to them that are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed vnto the headache, amongſt all new Wines theſe aboue named ſmall Wines are leaſt hurtfull, and maye be taken with leſſe ieoperdie. If anye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende that French, Clared and Gaſcone wine, and other wines as ſtrong as Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cone is, doe as little hurt to the head as theſe Wines doe: I aunſwere that the
<pb facs="tcp:3182:10"/> French, Clared and Gaſcone wines are not thin and ſubtill, but ſtrong, thicke and hote, and not as <hi>Galen</hi> ſayth <hi>aquoſa</hi> that is, wateriſh. Wherfore if the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of <hi>Galen</hi> may take place, their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is here openly confuted, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend ſo much French, Clared and Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cone Wine, and deſpiſe and condemne Rhenniſh and ſuch like White wines.<note place="margin">Rhenniſh and white wines for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to be vſed of ſome newe phiſitions.</note> The ſame men haue forbidden all their patientes that are diſpoſed to the ſtone, gout, and rewme, by name all Rhenniſh and white Wines, and ſaye that white and Rhenniſh Wines make and engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the goute, holding that white and Rhenniſhe Wine driue ſo ſore that they bring matter to the kidneis and bladder,<note place="margin">That white wines bring the matter of the ſtone to the kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes, and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore breede the ſtone by the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſome ſophisters.</note> whereof the ſtone is engendred. Firſt I muſt reaſon againſt this vnreaſonable reaſon more largely than the argument of this booke, in ſome mens opinion, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth, bicauſe they haue holden this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion ſo long and without authoritie or good reaſon teach it ſo ſliffelye ſtill. For the better diſcuſſing of this matter, it is néedefull to tell what things bréede and
<pb facs="tcp:3182:11"/> make the ſtone, and howe manye chiefe cauſes there be of it, and whether thin and wateriſh wines be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> materiall or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe of the ſtone, or no cauſe of it at all, but a preſeruatiue from the ſtone. Although the naturall diſpoſition that a man hath of his father or mother to the ſtone be a great and vnauoydable cauſe of the ſtone, yet beſide that, there are two common cauſes, of the which the one is the materiall cauſe, and the other is the cauſe efficient, or working or making cauſe, that maketh the ſtone, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter that is diſpoſed to be a ſtone. <hi>Galen</hi> in the third booke of noriſhmentes, writing of chéeſe in few wordes ſheweth both the materiall and efficient cauſe of the ſtone. Olde chéeſe,<note place="margin">Groſſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors are the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cauſe of the ſtone, &amp; burning heate the cauſe effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient.</note> ſayth he, is harder to digeſt and of worſe iuice, and therefore readier to bréede the ſtone, <hi>Nam vbi ſuccorum craſsities cum arde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti calore iungitur, illic calculi generantur,</hi> that is, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as there is groſſeneſſe of iuices ioyned with a burning heate, there are ſtones engendred. <hi>Galen</hi> I graunt in his booke of good and ill iuices, writeth that the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb facs="tcp:3182:11"/> vſe of ſuch medicines that make thin and cut groſſe humors in pieces,<note place="margin">Medicines that are ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e and make thin, and cut groſſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, to much vſed, make the blood whai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iſh, or cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lericke, or melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</note> maketh a mans bloud eyther whayiſh, or Chole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke or Melancholike, for ſuch kindes of Medicines doe not onely cut and make thin, but alſo heate out of meaſure. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and marke here that he ſpeaketh not of Rhenniſhe and white wine, but of vnmeaſurablye hote medicines, and he ſayth immediatlye after, <hi>ob id<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſolida membra exiccant, &amp; craſſum humo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem reddunt, quo in renibus aſſato, gignuntur calculi,</hi> that is. They drie vp the faſt and ſound members, and make the humor groſſe, whereof when as it is burned or roſted in the kidneyes, ſtones are ingendred. Thus farre <hi>Galen.</hi> The ſame ſentence and meaning hath <hi>Galen methodi medendi.</hi> 13.<note place="margin">Meates of groſſe iuice ingender the ſtone.</note> 
                        <hi>libro</hi> in theſe wordes, <hi>qui craſsi ſucci cibis veſcun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, calculi vitio vexantur.</hi> They that eate meates of groſſe iuice, are grieued with the diſeaſe of the ſtone. <hi>Aetius</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that the cauſes of the ſtone are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall crudities or rawneſſe, or vndige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted humors wherof is gathered togither
<pb facs="tcp:3182:12"/> great plenty of vndigeſted and raw mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, when a burning riſeth about the kidneys and bladder, which burneth them and maketh them go togither in one, and maketh therof an hard ſtone. <hi>Alexander Trallianus</hi> intreating of the ſtone, ſaith: <hi>Eſt materialis calculorum cauſa hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor craſſus, efficiens autem ignea ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liditas,</hi> the materiall cauſe of the ſtone is a groſſe humor, and the efficient cauſe is a fierie heate.</p>
                     <p>Now by theſe authorities that I haue alleaged, it is cleare vnto all them that can and will ſée that the matter or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall cauſe of the ſtone is a groſſe or thicke humor, and that the worker or ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe of the ſame is a great heate in or about the kidneyes or bladder. If that be graunted to be true, it followeth that thoſe meates and drinkes that are of groſſer ſubſtance and hoter than others be, cauſe and bréede the ſtone rather than other meates and drinkes that are thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, finer and of a colder complexion, but both French, Clared and Gaſcone Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wine are of groſſer and thicker ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:3182:12"/> and hoter of complexion than white Rhenniſh wine and white french wines be of.<note place="margin">Clared wine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be of Fraunce or of Gaſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and red wine with ſuch like, brede more the ſtone, than white and Rhen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh do, both concerning the materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe.</note> Therfore they bréede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone more than white Rhenniſh and whyte French Wines doe. The Rheniſh wine that is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly drunken in Gentlemens houſes and Citizens houſes is commonly a yere old at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt before it be drunken, &amp; therfore it is older than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> common Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wine, which dureth not commonlye aboue one yeare, and if Rhenniſh wyne be drunken within the yeare, it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly racked before it be drunken, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for two cauſes it hath fewer dregges and leſſe terreſtritie or groſſe earthlyneſſe than the Clared wine hath, and therfore bréedeth the ſtone leſſe than Clared wine that is commonly drunke in gentlemens houſes doth. If I can proue this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue ſayde, and alſo that Clared wine is hoter than white Rhenniſh and white French wines be, there is nothing to let me but I may conclude without anye withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that Clared or red wines bréede the ſtone more than white wines do. Which I will aſſaye to bring to paſſe after thys maner following.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:3182:13"/>
                     <head>Of the difference of wynes by the colors.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Plinie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth foure principall colors of Wine.</note>
                        <hi>PLinie</hi> in the .xiiij. booke of his naturall hyſtorie writeth thus of the colors of Wine. <hi>Colores vinis quatuor. Albus, fuluus, ſanguineus, niger,</hi> that is, wines haue ſower colors: white, rediſh yellowe, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine and black. The white is well kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen to all our countriemen, but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are not fullye knowen euen vnto ſome of the learned here in Englande. Wherefore I thinke it néedefull for the better vnderſtanding of it that I ſhall entreat of hereafter, to declare theſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, ſo that they maye be knowen of all men that reade this booke. <hi>Aulus Gelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in his ſecond booke <hi>de noctibus atticis cap.</hi> 26.<note place="margin">Fuluus.</note> writeth, that <hi>Fuluus color vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detur de rufo at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> viridi miſtus eſſe.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">There are diuerſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees vini fului.</note> that is, the color that is called in Latine <hi>Fuluus,</hi> ſéemeth to be menged with red and gréene, and there ſéemeth in ſome to be more gréene, and in other more red. And he writeth that the color called <hi>Fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Flauꝰ color.</note>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3182:13"/> in Latine ſéemeth to be made of the mengling togither of grene, red &amp; white. And he writeth that the color of the lion,<note place="margin">Leo fuluus, Aurum fuluum.</note> golde, and ſande is named <hi>Fuluus</hi> in Latine, thus farre <hi>Gellius.</hi> Whereas <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> writeth of wines he hath theſe words folowing. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> which wordes <hi>Ruellius</hi> tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateth thus. <hi>Giluu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vtpote quod mediu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, medias inter vtrun<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> vires habet.</hi> But <hi>Cornarius</hi> in this place turneth <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> into <hi>fuluum.</hi> And in dede I lyke better the tranſlation of <hi>Cornarius</hi> in this place, than the tranſlation of <hi>Ruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi> otherwiſe an eloquent and learned man, wherevnto moueth me the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Galen</hi> of our <hi>Linacre</hi> written in his xij. booke <hi>de methodo medendi. Ne<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> inuenies ex alborum vinorum genere calidum vllum, quando auſtera &amp; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocriter alba, cum inueterauerine fuluiora quodammodo reddantur. Quod ſi aliter nominare fuluum co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem velis, licet voces igneum pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lens. Quotquot autem in ipſis cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſsima
<pb facs="tcp:3182:14"/> ſunt omnia certè flaua ſunt.</hi> Theſe wordes peraduenture ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gentleman or other learned men, had leuer reade in Greeke than in the Latine or Engliſhe alone, for whoſe ſakes I will rehearſe <hi>Galens</hi> owne wordes in his owne tongue, that men maye iudge the better of the nature of the woordes, and thereby of <hi>Galens</hi> meaning, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Out of all theſe places of the authours that I haue alleadged, I gather that <hi>Fuluus color</hi> is it that a man may call in Engliſh, rediſh yelow, for as <hi>Virgill</hi> calleth Golde <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum,</hi> bicauſe it is rediſhe yellow, our countrymen marking in golde both a roadneſſe and alſo a yellowneſſe, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſaye, that a thing is as red as gold,
<pb facs="tcp:3182:14"/> and other whiles, that a thing is as yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low as gold, as commonlye they ſay that his eyes &amp; ſkin that hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſeaſe that is called in Duch, Die guel ſucht, and the Northe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Engliſh tongue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Guelſought, and in Southerne Engliſh, the yellowe iaundiſe, are as yelow as gold. This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is named in Latin <hi>Aurigo</hi> of <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius Celſus,</hi> of the color of gold. <hi>Galen</hi> ſéeming to doubt whether al men vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode what he ment by this word <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> which <hi>Hippocrates</hi> vſeth in this ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, taketh the paine to open and ſhewe by two other Gréeke words what he meaneth by <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, ſaying that he thynketh that <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> maye bée called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that is, Wine of a fierye color, hauing mixed therewith the color of yellow Ochar, which Ochar is not of a bright yellowe color as <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is, but more darker, whereby a man may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly know that <hi>Fuluum</hi> which is called in Gréeke <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> is a rediſh yellow color,<note place="margin">Fieriſh yellow.</note> as our Muſcadine and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards are, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they come to vs are of.<note place="margin">Vinum ſanguineu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                        <hi>Vinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanguineum,</hi> that is ſanguine, or
<pb facs="tcp:3182:15"/> bloud coloured Wine, it is that we call commonly in Engliſh Clared wine, but not the pale, or pallet (as ſome call it) Clared wine. <hi>Vinum nigrum,</hi> ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of <hi>Plinie,</hi> and called <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, in Greeke, is fooliſhly, but commonlye called in Engliſh red wine, when as it ought to be called blacke Wine, of the blacke color that it hath in compariſon of other wines. And now after that I haue ſhewed what the foure colors that <hi>Plinie</hi> maketh mention of, betoken in our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh tongue, I will go forwarde to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the natures of Wines by their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall colors.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the nature and properties of white Wines.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DIoſcorides</hi> ſayth, <hi>vinum albu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tenue ſtomacho vtile, ac fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile in membra diſtribuitur.</hi> That is, white wine is thin, and good for the ſtomach, and is eaſily co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed into the members,<note place="margin">White wine both in ſickeneſſe &amp; in health is rather to be choſen than other wines by the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſcoriaes.</note> and white wine both in ſickneſſe and in health is rather
<pb facs="tcp:3182:15"/> to be choſen tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others. And <hi>Galen</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the nature of white Wine, ſayth: <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. That is, ye can finde none of the white wines that is hote, meaning of the common white wines that were about where as he dwelt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Out of Galen in his fift booke de locis affectis.</head>
                     <p>FVrthermore, when as a certain yong man being a Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marian, as often as he did to earneſtlye teach, or deuiſe of any matter, or waxed hungry or angrye, was taken with the falling ſickneſſe, by reaſon of the to much quick feling of the mouth of his ſtomacke: I commaunded to giue vnto him bread well prepared in the thirde or fourth houre alone, if he did not thirſt. But if he were troubled with thirſt, to be moyſtened in wine,<note place="margin">White wine mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurably binding hurteth not the head.</note> and that in white wine which meaſurably bindeth, for ſuch wine, as it ſtrengthneth the ſtomach, ſo it hurteth not the head as hote wines are wont to do. Thus farre <hi>Galen.</hi> Out
<pb facs="tcp:3182:16"/> of whoſe wordes we maye gather howe vnreaſonable and vnlearned they be in <hi>Galens</hi> workes, that ſaye that all white Wines whether they be Rhenniſhe or French, or of like nature with eyther of both, are hurtfull for the rheume and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſeaſes of the head, and forbid their patientes to drinke them for a table or common drinke to be taken with meat, when as <hi>Galen</hi> alloweth it for them that haue the falling ſickneſſe, and ſayth that it doth not hurt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomach, neyther trouble y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head as hote wines do, of which ſortes they alow ſome for their patients for common table wine, as diuerſe kinds of Clared wine, whereof euery one of them is hotter and more headie and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh than the common Rhenniſhe and French wines are, of the which matter we will talke hereafter more largelye, if God will. That the thin, ſmall and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriſh wines do not hurt the head, ſo that they haue a littell aſtriction, <hi>Galen</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth plainly in his booke <hi>de euchymia &amp; cacochymia,</hi> in theſe words. And eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as firiſh red wines, ſeeing that they are
<pb facs="tcp:3182:16"/> hote of nature, by and by fill the head,<note place="margin">Fieriſh red wines fill the head by and by, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they be hote.</note> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo thoſe wines that are thin and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriſh, and gently binding, are not onlye vnhurtfull vnto the head, but alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time they take away thoſe ſmall head a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches which come of humors gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither in the ſtomach.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Out of Aetius.</head>
                     <p>OF all wines,<note place="margin">Which wines hurte leaſt the head and ſinewes.</note> white wines are leaſt hurt, wateriſh wines ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bréedeth the head ache, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hurt the ſinewes. Wines that are white in color, nouriſh leaſt of all other Wines, if they be thin in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, and after a maner like vnto wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">Aetius al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth white wine for a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue againſt the ſtone.</note> 
                        <hi>Aetius</hi> alſo preſcribing a diet for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are deliuered of the ſtone, how that they maye be preſerued from falling into the diſeaſe of the ſtone againe, alloweth a ſmall wine that prouoketh water, and is not verie olde. And the author of the booke of healing of the ſtone which is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed vnto <hi>Galen,</hi> and iudged of manye to be his, in expreſſe wordes fayth as followeth here. <hi>Vinum ſit tenue admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum
<pb facs="tcp:3182:17"/> &amp; album, non ita vetus, dulcia verò &amp; nigra vina, calculoſis ſunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>epta.</hi> That is, let your wines be verye ſmall and white,<note place="margin">Red that is Clared wine is not good for the ſtone.</note> and not ſo olde, but ſwéete wines and blackiſh red wines are verye vnméete for them that haue the ſtone. And the author ſayeth in the ſame booke a littell after. <hi>Vinum tibi conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit tenue &amp; album, quod miſturam non ita patitur</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>nam eiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi facile deſcendit, &amp; ſuccos qui ſunt in nobis attenuat &amp; ſecernit per vrinas, virtutem<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> roborat.</hi> That is, white and ſmall wine is good and méete for you, which being ſmall, cannot abide to be menged with much water, for ſuch wine doth eaſilye go downe, and maketh ſubtill or fine the iuices or humors that are in vs, and ſifteth them out by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſtrengthneth the power of man.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the natures of white and diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wynes, taken out of Actuarius the laſt of the noble Greeke writers of phiſicke.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3182:17"/>
                     <p>GRoſſe and thicke wines nouryſh much,<note place="margin">Groſſe or thick wines.</note> 
                        <note place="margin">Thin or ſubtill wines.</note> and are cauſe of groſſe bloud, and of the ſtopping of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward partes, but thin or ſubtill wines which driue out water, are of a contrarye nature,<note place="margin">Rediſh yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low wines are hoteſt of all. Wines in color red, are next in heat to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh yellow. Leaſt hote of all are wateriſh and ſmall wines, and they trouble the head leaſt. A ſmall white wine is best for a common ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble wine.</note> for they engender fine or thin bloud. Some wines that haue a little aſtriction, are better for the ſtomach but nouriſh leſſe, but ſwéete wines are of the contrarie nature, but white wines are leſſe hote tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other wines. Of wines are hoteſt of all rediſh yellow, and next vnto them are hoteſt, Wines of red co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor, they are leaſt hote that are wateriſh, which are called in Greke <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they wil not ſuffer to be delayed w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> much water, ſuch wines as theſe do trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the head leaſt. But ſtrong and wel co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lored wine are more fit for them that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor for to be of a good plite, and to looke well. But for thée that careſt only for thy ſimple health, and for thy liuely ſpirite, it maye ſéeme that a weake wine which is white and thin ſhould he ſufficient for thee, and thou ought therewith to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, except thou be compelled to flie for
<pb facs="tcp:3182:18"/> néedes ſake to vſe hoter wines when as thou art to much cooled in thy body.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the nature of red wine, which here in England is commonly called Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wyne, and of the nature of blacke wine which is called commonlye in England red wine, out of Galen in his thirde booke de ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis.</head>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Red wine and thicke wine.</note>IF that whatſoeuer doth noriſh, be meat, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is wine to be placed among the number of meates (that is of things that doe féede and encreaſe the bodie.<note place="margin">No color of any wine is liker to bloud, than it that we call Clared wine, for the blacke wine that we call red wine, is blacker tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it may be compared vnto bloud. Rufa at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> craſſa vina. Deinceps nigra. Rufa aut nigra craſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtringentia.</note>) Of all wines red and thicke wines are moſt méete to make bloud, as ſuch as néede little chaunging to be turned into bloud, after theſe folow in order blacke wines, groſſe and ſwéete, and alſo thoſe which in color is red and blacke, and in ſubſtance or compoſition are thick, ioyned with a binding quality. The ſame ſentence hath <hi>Aetius</hi> in theſe words following. <hi>Rufa ita<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> &amp; craſſa
<pb facs="tcp:3182:18"/> ex omnibus ad ſanguinem generan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum commodiſsima ſunt, vt quae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua egeant in ſanguinem tranſmutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one. Deinceps nigra ſimul dulcia ac craſſa. Deinde colore quidem rufa aut nigra, compage vero craſſa, &amp; haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſimul adſtringentem qualitatem.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Out of the fourth booke of Galen de ſauitate tuenda.</head>
                     <p>REfuſe and flie thicke and blacke wines, bicauſe they make an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill iuice, and enter thorow and go very ſlowly down, and in the fift booke he ſayth. Such wines as tarie long in the bellie, are none of them fit for an olde man, and that blacke wines that are groſſe and thicke, and are binding, tarie and abide long in the bellie and ſtir vp flowinges in it. But they that are blacke and thick, and haue no aſtriction, in déede they tarie ſhorter while in the bellie. But yet they ſtirre not a man to make water, ſome take them before meat but they are not good for olde men, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3182:19"/> any other which make a thick iuice, for theſe ſtop the liuer, milt and kidneys, whereby it commeth to paſſe that ſome olde men vſing theſe more largelye, fall into the dropſey, and other fall into the ſtone.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the nature of wynes of diuers and ſundry colors out of Galen de methodo medendi, ſexto &amp; .12.</head>
                     <p>IN the ſixt booke. Whatſoeuer Wines be ſwéete, and alſo of a readiſh yelow color, all ſuch are ſharpe or biting, and hote aboue meaſure.<note place="margin">Wines good for them that ſwounde.</note> In the .xij. booke. To them that ſwoune by the reaſon of yellow gall that vexeth the mouth of the ſtomache, a colde drinke is to be giuen vnto them, yet for all that wine that is hote of nature, and doth further the conneyance of iuices in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the bodie, ought to be offred to al them that are vexed with ſwounding, for it is plainly our will, that the nouriſhment that is taken in, ſhould be delt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed
<pb facs="tcp:3182:19"/> into the bodye, and that it ſhoulde not tarie in the ſtomach, but it is openly knowen that of wines they ought to be choſen that are yelow in color,<note place="margin">Wines yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in color and fine in ſubſtance are beſt for fainting or ſwouning.</note> of a fine ſubſtance and olde, and ſuch muſt néedes be of a good ſmell.</p>
                     <p>To them that fall in a ſwounding by to much plentie of rawe humors, groſſe thicke wines are noyſome, and waterye wines as vnprofitable are to be eſchued. Therefore we muſt chooſe out thoſe that are midle wines, which, as is before ſayd, are yellowe and white. But ſo manye wines as are the hoteſt of all, are bright yelow in color, as is the wine called <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubum</hi> in Italie.</p>
                     <p>Of other kindes of wine they that are ſoure with aſtriction,<note place="margin">Auſtera alba.</note> and méetelye white and thicke, are not fit for the conueyance or leading of iuices into the bodie.<note place="margin">Vina au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtera alba antiqua.</note> But if they be olde inough, if ye haue no other, ye maye vſe them, for all ſuch when they are old are good for the ſtomach.<note place="margin">Rediſh yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low wine trouble the head.</note> Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more all wines that ſmell well and are rediſh yellow, ſo much as is of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture altogither, they trouble the heade
<pb facs="tcp:3182:20"/> when a man is vexed with both kindes of ſwounding, that is of it that commeth of yellow gall, and alſo it that commeth of great plentie of rawe humors falling into the mouth of the ſtomach, and there is no conuenient wine as is required, and thou art néedes compelled to vſe ſome wine, thou muſt flie as I haue ſaid before, all ſoure aſtringent wines, and new wines,<note place="margin">Old thin or wateriſh wines are lightly ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into the body.</note> and thicke wines, and choſe wateriſh wines, and of them ſuch as are olde, for ſuch wines although they do not mightily heat, yet they are led or caried lightly into the body, wherefore theſe doe all alike conuey and deale the noriſhing iuices into the body,<note place="margin">Both red yellowiſh and olde ſmall wine conuey and deale the iuices into the bodie alike.</note> as red yellow wines do, yet there is a difference betwéene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, that the rediſh yellow wines are more profitable for the digeſtion that is in the ſtomach, and in the veynes, bicauſe they doe heate more. Moreouer, they are eaſie to be tempered (or elſe as <hi>Linaker</hi> tranſlateth it, to be mixed) &amp; therfore are profitable to make good iuice. But there is none of all theſe things in wateriſhe wines, for verie little of the ſubſtance of
<pb facs="tcp:3182:20"/> theſe is turned into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinde of bloud.<note place="margin">Rediſh yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low wines ſmite the head.</note> But when as rediſh yellowe wine ſmite the head, they that are wateriſhe doe neuer trouble it, and they beyonde all other driue out water. Next vnto the which are rediſh yellowe wines that are moſt thin and ſubtill,<note place="margin">Small wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriſh wines driue out piſſe moſt of all other wines.</note> which alſo ought to be choſen moſt chieflly againſt ſwounding. Yelow wines that are groſſeſt in ſubſtance are conueyed into the bodie more ſlowlie tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe be, howbeit they are more piercing then all ſoure and binding wines, but theſe rediſh yellowe wines againe doe nouriſh more than thin wines, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect fautie iuices, of all other wines moſt ſpeedily engendring a good bloud. Thus farre <hi>Galen.</hi> Nowe after that it is often inough proued by the beſt authors that euer wrote of Phiſick, that all red wines as are our Clared wines, and all blacke wines, which we call red wines, are ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and groſſer in ſubſtaunce than ſmall white wines be of: and both driue out water leſſe than ſmall white wines doe: It followeth that Clared and red wines are more, both the materiall and effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:3182:21"/> cauſes of the ſtone, than ſmall white wines are.</p>
                     <p>Where as ſome argue that ſuch wines as driue moſt, bring humors moſt of all other to the kidneys,<note place="margin">The argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of them that holde that Rhenniſh and white wines breede the ſtone more than other wines doe.</note> water veſſels, and bladder, whereof the ſtone is ingendered there. But ſmall Rhenniſh wine and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſmall white wines driue humors moſt to the places before named, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they breede the ſtone more than other wines that driue not ſo much as they do: I anſwere vnto the <hi>maior,</hi> that not eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wine that driueth moſt humors vnto the kidneys, water veſſels &amp; bladder is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greateſt bréeder &amp; engendrer of the ſtone. For although ſmall and wateriſh whyte wines driue more than Clared, yet it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth not that they bréede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone more than red and Clared wines doe. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they driue ſome kinde of humors vnto the places aboue rehearſed: yet doe they not leaue them ſticking faſt in thoſe places, but they driue them quite thorow all the water veſſelles into the chamber pot or vrinall, for the which cauſe they are called in Gréeke <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that is,
<pb facs="tcp:3182:21"/> driuers forth of water and vrine, and ſuch things as are in the vrine. Which name they haue not, bicauſe (as ſome men doe dreame) they bring many humors wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the ſtone is made, to the kidneys and bladder, and let them lie there, as it were rotting in a dunghill, but as a faire and thin water caſten into a canel of a ſtréete if it haue one to driue it forwarde, not onelye carieth it ſelfe awaye forth of the towne into the common ſinke that is without the towne, but alſo the filthines that hath bene in the canell long before, euen ſo that ſmall white wine that hath a nature to driue forth it ſelfe, and with it other things that are neceſſarie to be driuen out by the vrine, bréedeth not hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors in the water veſſelles, but driueth them quite away, and ſuffereth them not to tarie there, how then can white wine that after this manner ſcoureth the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter veſſels be an ingendrer of the matter of the ſtone, when as it driueth the ſame matter away, and will not ſuffer it to ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in thoſe places where as the ſtone v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to be ingendred. When I was a
<pb facs="tcp:3182:22"/> ſcholer in Cambridge, there was there a ſtinking butcherie, and very noyſome to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that went by it, or through it, what if a man ſhould haue bene hired for .xl.s. in the yeare to keepe the butcherie, &amp; the reſt of the towne ſwéete, by carying out of the puddings, guts, and ſtinking bloud? if this fellow ſhould carie out all the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe out of the butcherie once in the wéeke vnto the market hill, and let it lie there, ſhould this man iuſtly be called a ſcourer or clenſer of the towne, that cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the filth therof from one place onlye to another, &amp; not quite out of the towne? I think no. Euen ſo if ſmal white wines ſhould driue humors from diuerſe places of the bodie, and ſhoulde not carrie them forth by the water veſſelles, but let them lie ſtinking there, it ought not to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a ſcourer but a defiler, &amp; an hurter of the bodie. If the maiſter of the pudding cart before named, would let the filthines of the butcherie tarie ſo long there vntill it ſtanke ſo ſore, by reaſon of long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in that place, and for lacke of ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying out betime, that both they of the
<pb facs="tcp:3182:22"/> butcherie, and all the neighbours about were grieuouſlye vexed with the foule ſtinke of that filth that taried ſo long there, if an other carter offred for the ſame wages euery ſeconde day to carie out all the vncleanneſſe of the towne, which of theſe two me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were more worthy to haue the office and name of the towneſcourer? Smal white wines ſcoure and driue out the vncleanneſſe of the bodie as much as it is poſſible to be done by them, and red and Clared wine ſtoppe and hold backe, and fill the bodie full of ill humors, now which are moſt profitable to be taken moſt commonly of a man for the kéeping of his health? But although ſmall white wine by nature hath ſuch properties to driue out by vrine vnprofitable humors, that are commed within the compaſſe of their working, yet the vertue of it is hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, either if the man by eating and drinking to much continually fill the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die with ſo many excrementes, that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture euen being holpen with white wine cannot driue them out, by reaſon of the ouerflowing plentie of them, alſo if that
<pb facs="tcp:3182:23"/> the meat lie to long in the ſtomach, and the excrements to long in the guttes, and goe not downe at conuenient times to the ſtoole.<note place="margin">White wine ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time cannot driue out humors ſufficiently if it be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by ill diet.</note> Than the white wine for lacke of helpe, can not doe his office. And it is plaine, that banketting and much eating and drinking and keeping of the meat to long in the ſtomache, and the excrements vnſcoured out of the bellie, giue the moſt part of the material cauſe vnto the ſtone, which thing may be eaſilye proued by the authority of <hi>Aetius</hi> writing of the ſtone, in theſe wordes.<note place="margin">The mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall cauſe of the ſtone.</note> Ye muſt beware of ſuch meats as are hard of ſubſtance, and are not eſie to be broken with chowing, and alſo them that haue much ſubſtance,<note place="margin">Holding of humors to long in the body, is the cauſe of the ſtone, and not the dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of them forth dayly in good ſeaſon.</note> and nouriſh verye much, and thoſe that are conueyed in by heapes into the bodie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they be fully digeſted, or made ripe, alſo meates of an heauy qualitie, and are hardly chaunged and ſwim aboue, and go to ſlowly downe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> belly, &amp; fill it ful of wind. Flie alſo ſuch as ſtop the ways and veynes of the bodie, or otherwiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide to long in the bellies, for the bellie being made wearie with ſuch meates,
<pb facs="tcp:3182:23"/> ſendeth them forth either as yet raw, or halfe ſodden to the liuer and kidneyes, and ſo it that was brought in by heapes rawe, is ſifted or ſtreyned vnfitlye and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nature, and with an haſtie rage is caried to the kidneyes, and by and by it groweth togither, and is thickned, and ſtandeth there ſtill. Thus farre <hi>Aetius.</hi> Of whome we may learne plainly howe the ſtone is made, and of what cauſes, and that neither ſmall white wine, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any other wine, will preſerue a man from the ſtone, except he kéepe good diet withall, and emptie out the excrements of the bellie dailye. And the ſame ſayth afterward, <hi>ventrem ſemper probè la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xum habere oportet. Hic enim ſi bene ſubierit, puriora lotia prodibunt.</hi> That is, ye muſt haue your bellie alway well loſed, for if the bellie worke well downeward, your water ſhall come forth the fairer and cleaner.</p>
                     <p>If ſo often emptying of the bellye as nature requireth, maketh a mans water cleare and faire, then the to much ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the bodie maketh a foule, drouſie
<pb facs="tcp:3182:24"/> or dreggye water. But ſuch foule geare bréedeth the ſtone, therfore to much ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of the bellye is oft the cauſe of the ſtone. For when as ſuch plentie of filthie matter cometh forth by the water, there muſt néedes be much aboue in the kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes and bladder, wherof the ſtone may be ingendred, if there be anye exceſſiue heate in the kidneyes and bladder. All men therefore may plainly ſée that ſmall white wine is falſlye accuſed to be a brée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the ſtone, when as ill diet and the ſtopping of ill humors within the bodye, is the cauſe thereof, and that wines that are hoter and ſtronger than white and Rhenniſh wines be, engender rewmes, and bréede the goute more than the white ſmall wines do, as it is by places aboue alleaged, fully prooued.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the natures of wynes after their taſtes.</head>
                     <p>THe wines that are commonlye brought into England, named by their taſtes in Gréeke <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,
<pb facs="tcp:3182:24"/> that in Latine, <hi>vina dulcia, aſtringentia, auſtera &amp; acerba,</hi> and ſuch like as are <hi>acria</hi> and <hi>acida,</hi> for the moſt part wherof we haue neuer one proper name in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, though we can name <hi>dulce vinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> well in Engliſh ſwéete wine: but what ſhall we call <hi>acre, auſterum</hi> and <hi>acer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bum</hi> in common vſed Engliſh? ſurely I cannot tell, for I cannot giue to euery one of theſe wordes one ſeuerall vſed Engliſh word, without circumlocution, wherfore ſéeing that the proper Engliſh wordes are ſo harde to be found: and the meaning of the words are as little kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen of the moſt part of all men, I think it ſhall be neceſſarye to ſhewe by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of ſome old learned writer, what theſe words <hi>adſtringens, auſterum</hi> and <hi>acerbum, acer</hi> and <hi>acidus</hi> doe ſignifie and betoken. If any man ſay that I nede not to take this paine, bicauſe the great and coſtlye booke, called <hi>Theſaurus linguae Romanae &amp; Britannicae,</hi> that is, the treaſure of the Latin and Engliſh tongue, hath done that thing alreadie: I
<pb facs="tcp:3182:25"/> aunſwere that I aſked counſell of that great booke, and in dede as I found great plentie both of good Latin wordes, and fine maners of ſpeaking, gathered wyth great paines, and ordered with no ſmall learning and iudgement: but in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, as I found to much plentie of light, and new inckhorne termes: ſo in ſome places I founde ſuch ſcarceneſſe, lacke, and want of proper and true Engliſhe names, that the author is faine to giue one name to diuerſe Latin wordes, for when I looked how he engliſhed <hi>Acer,</hi> he engliſheth it thus. Eger, ſharpe, tart, ſoure or fell. Lo, here is great plentie of wordes, and yet we can not tell what <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> in taſte doth properly ſignifie, and a litle after he writeth theſe wordes, <hi>acer, acidus ſuccus, Vitruuius,</hi> eger. By this booke we may Engliſh <hi>lac acidum,</hi> eger milke. And afterwarde where as of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe he expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth what <hi>Acidus</hi> betoke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, he engliſheth it, eger, ſoure, ſharp, and he engliſheth <hi>acidula pira,</hi> foure peares, he engliſheth <hi>Acerbum,</hi> vnripe, ſoure, diſpleaſant, and <hi>Acerbitas,</hi> ſoure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:3182:25"/> of taſte, ſharpneſſe or grieuouſneſſe of time. He engliſheth <hi>Auſterus,</hi> ſoure, ſharpe, vnpleaſant, and <hi>guſtus auſterus</hi> a rough or ſoure taſt.</p>
                     <p>Now how ſhall a man know by this booke what difference is betwéene, <hi>acer, acidus, auſterus</hi> and <hi>acerbus,</hi> when as he calleth them all ſoure, and putteth ſo ſmall difference betwéene one and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Surely we haue but ſmall helpe of that booke in declaring of theſe words, &amp; many ſuch other, that are much occupied in phiſicke and philoſophy, and in other both liberall and mathematical ſciences. Wherfore I wiſhe, to the ende that the booke may be in dede as it is called: that one learned phiſition &amp; philoſopher like vnto <hi>Linaker,</hi> one olde and learned gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian like vnto <hi>Clemond,</hi> and one perfite Engliſhman like vnto Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Moore,</hi> had the amendment and making perſite of this booke commited vnto them. But now as <hi>Terence</hi> ſayeth, <hi>quoniam hac no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſucceſsit, alia aggre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diendum eſt via. Galen</hi> in the firſt of his bookes that he writeth of the powers
<pb facs="tcp:3182:26"/> of ſimple medicines ſayth. Cap. 39. If any man doe taſte quinces or apples, or med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, or mirtels, doubtleſſe he ſhall know that there is an other féeling that is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnto vs of theſe things in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tongue, and another of bodies <hi>aſtringentibus,</hi> that is, that are onely binding, for thoſe things that are binding, appeare to driue inwarde that part of vs that they touche in al places equally or in like, as pulling, ſtopping, as drawing togither. But <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtera</hi> ſéeme to goe downe euen vnto the bottome, and to moue a rough and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal féeling and drying vp and waſting all the moiſture of féeling bodies. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore when as that bodie which is moued vnto our tongue doth mightilye drie and draw togither, and maketh it rough euen to the bottome, as choke peares that are not ripe, and cornelles, euerye ſuch is called <hi>acerbum,</hi> differing from <hi>auſtero</hi> in the exceſſe of theſe qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities. That is to ſay, <hi>auſterum</hi> in many things is like vnto <hi>acerbo,</hi> but <hi>acerbum</hi> is in all thoſe things wherein they are ſomething like, much ſtronger and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier
<pb facs="tcp:3182:26"/> than <hi>auſterum</hi> is: and <hi>Galen</hi> in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place writeth, that aſtringent is weaker than <hi>acerbum</hi> and <hi>auſterum,</hi> in all thoſe properties that they haue anye likeneſſe in. And <hi>Galen</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ix. booke <hi>de ſimplicium medicamentorum facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus,</hi> ſayeth that <hi>adſtringentia</hi> draw togither, bind togither, and do make thick our ſubſtance, and therfore vpon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer part of our bodie they be layde without, by and by they make it full of wrinkles, and draw togither. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of <hi>Galen,</hi> we may perceiue in ſome kindes of peares, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked at diuerſe times, <hi>guſtum acerbum, auſterum &amp; aſtringentem.</hi> When the peares are newly growen, if ye taſte of them at the firſt, ye ſhall perceyue that they are harde and drie, and are verye rough in taſte, and then they are called <hi>acerba,</hi> but after that they are more than halfe ripe, when that hardneſſe and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is gone, then become they moyſter and ſofter, and are in taſte <hi>auſtera.</hi> And when they are full ripe, they are <hi>aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia,</hi> with a ſwéete taſte ioyned ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.
<pb facs="tcp:3182:27"/> By this diſcription, I truſt wiſe and learned men by taking of ſome paine in reading of olde Engliſh writers ſhall come by the knowledge of right and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Engliſh wordes for theſe .iij. Latin, or els at the leaſt I iudge that men ſhall vnderſtande what difference is betweene <hi>aſtringens, auſterum</hi> and <hi>acerbum.</hi> In the meane time vntill that we may ſpede better, we may engliſh <hi>aſtringens,</hi> bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>auſterum,</hi> ſoure binding, and <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerbum,</hi> rough and binding like choke peares. And <hi>Galen lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ſimpl. medic. facultatibus. cap.</hi> 39. and in diuerſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places maketh an open and plaine difference betweene <hi>acre</hi> and <hi>acidum,</hi> contrarie to it that is alleaged of <hi>Vitru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius,</hi> who maketh them both one. For <hi>Galen</hi> ſayeth, that <hi>acria</hi> are <hi>calida,</hi> and that <hi>acida</hi> are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>old.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Acer</hi> may be Engliſhed biting ſharp, and <hi>acidum</hi> may be named ſoure as ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, and ſoure milke, and diuers other things. <hi>Actius</hi> writeth, that wine that is ſoure with an harriſh binding, ſo that it be well ſmelling withall, hurteth the
<pb facs="tcp:3182:27"/> head, but it which is wateriſhe,<note place="margin">Wateriſh wines ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther brede the headach neither hurt the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, then when as the gout is the hurting of the ſinewes and ioyntes how engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſmall wateriſh wines the gout?</note> neither bréedeth the headach, neither hurteth the ſinewes. <hi>Galen</hi> alſo ſayth that ſoure bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wines ſtoppe flowings, and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the ſtomach, and hurt not the head, but that they helpe not them that are fallen into a ſwounde.</p>
                     <p>Wines that are rough and binding in taſte like vnto choke peares, ſtop vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and flowings of the belly, and they coole and drie. Moreouer they goe hardlye downe, when as thoſe things that are only of a ſoure taſte, go eaſily downe.</p>
                     <p>I haue learned by experience (ſayeth <hi>Galen</hi>) that all thoſe things that binde, and are alſo ſoure, are manifeſtly cold.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Simeon Sethi</hi> ſayeth, wines that are a little and gently binding, &amp; are in color<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, and in ſubſtance thin, are good for them that are of a good and a meane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion and temperature. But they are of a good complexion and of a mean tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature that are neither to hote nor to colde, neither to moyſt nor to drie, of the which ſort I wéene we ſhall finde as few at this time almoſt, as we ſhalbe able to
<pb facs="tcp:3182:28"/> finde citizens of <hi>Platoes</hi> common welth in euery pariſh of England. And <hi>Galen</hi> a man of more authoritie than <hi>Simeon Sethi</hi> is of, writeth in the booke of good and euill iuices, that as fierie red wines, for aſmuch as they are hote in working, by and by fill the heade, euen ſo thoſe wines that are thin and wateriſhe, and doe lightly bind, not only are not vnnoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome vnto the head, but alſo take awaye ſmall headaches, and he ſaith afterward, all wines that are binding, are comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for the ſtomache, and that ſuch as are ſoure and colde, be of ſubtill partes, but they that are binding, are of groſſe parts <hi>de ſimplie. med. facultatib. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 2.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Of ſweete wines.</note>Whatſoeuer things are ſwéete, cannot be colde, therfore ſwéete wines are of an hote complexion: and <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> ſayth, ſweete wines hath groſſe partes in it, and doth breath out of the bodie more hardlye, it filleth the ſtomache full of winde, it troubleth the bellye, and the guttes as <hi>Muſt</hi> doth, but it maketh not a man ſo ſone drunken, but it is moſt fit
<pb facs="tcp:3182:28"/> of all other for the kidneys &amp; the bladder.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To whom wine is ill, and vnmete and verie hurtfull.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ARiſtotell</hi> ſayeth that wine is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fit for children, nor nurſes, and <hi>Galen</hi> counſayleth that chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall taſte no wine at all: and woulde, that not euen ſpringoldes that are full growen, ſhoulde take wine but in ſmall quantitie, bicauſe that it maketh them fall headlongs into wrath and into luſt of the bodie, and maketh the reaſonable part of the minde dull and drouſie. Wine is ill alſo for them that are of a hote burning complexion, and haue any inflammation within them in their bodies, or haue any burning agues. It is alſo generallye ill for them that haue a great reume and the goute, or ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an halfe or hole palſey. The wine that is menged with <hi>Gipſo</hi> or with Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſter, as Sacke is, hurteth the ſinewes, and maketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head heauy, &amp; ſetteth it on fier, and is very ill for the bladder. Wine
<pb facs="tcp:3182:29"/> that is menged with cute, as our Malm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey is, fill a mans head and make hym drunken, breath out more hardlye, and trouble the ſtomache, which wordes I iudge, ought to be vnderſtanded of ſuch a wine, as hath very much cute put into it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>To whome and for what purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes wine is good.</head>
                     <p>THe holy ſcripture ſayeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wine maketh the hart of man merie, and that it is good to be taken of them that haue a weake and a féeble ſtomach, and the .xxxj. chapter of the Prouerbes hath this ſaying, O La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell, giue not vnto kings, I ſay, vnto kings, wine to drinke of it, or to princes ſtrong drinke, leaſt they, after they haue drunken, forget the law that is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or ouerthrow the cauſes of all poore mens children. Giue ſtrong drinke vnto them that are condemned to die, and Wine to them that haue a ſorowfull hart, that after they haue drunken, they maye forget their pouertie, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb facs="tcp:3182:29"/> no more their miſfortune.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Galen</hi> in his firſt booke <hi>de ſanitate tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda,</hi> ſayeth that wine molſteneth and nouriſheth whatſoeuer is before made drie out of meaſure, and alſo ſwageth and ouercommeth the ſharpeneſſe of bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter gall, and furthermore, emptieth out by ſweate, and driueth forth by water.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Out of Dioſcorides .xj. chapter of the fift booke.</head>
                     <p>GEnerally euery wine not mixed, and is only ſimple of himſelfe, and is of nature in taſte ſoure and binding, maketh hote, is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily conueyed into the bodie, it is good for the ſtomache, it maketh a man haue an appetite, it noriſheth and maketh a man ſléepe, ſtrengthneth and maketh a good color, and if it be plenteouſlye drunken,<note place="margin">Wines good againſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> helpeth them that haue taken Hemlocke, or Coriander, or the poiſon called Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> poiſon called Iria or Opium, which is the iuice of Poppy, or Litharge, or Eugh, or Wolfes bayne, or choking muſhromes, or todeſtooles. It is alſo
<pb facs="tcp:3182:30"/> good againſt al the bitings and ſtingings of all créeping beaſtes, which after they haue ſtinged or bitten, kill a man with colde, or ouerthrowe the ſtomach. It is good for the long continuaunce of windi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the midrife, and againſt the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the ſtomach, and hitchcocke or yeſking, and againſt bending or ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching out of the ſtomach, and againſt the flowing of the guttes and bellye. Wine is alſo good to them that ſweate much,<note place="margin">Wine good for them that ſweate to much.</note> and are made faint with to much ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and eſpeciallie ſuch as is white, olde and well ſmelling. Hitherto <hi>Dioſcoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</hi> Whoſe words when as he ſpeaketh of the holeſonineſſe of wines againſt poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and the bitings and ſtingings of venemous beaſtes, muſt be vnderſtanded of Muſcadine, Sack, Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ſey and Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtarde, and ſuch hote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their heate, enter farther into the body, and more ſpéedily, and are better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt cold poiſons tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> colder wines be.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Simeon Sethi of the nature of Wines.</head>
                     <pb facs="tcp:3182:30"/>
                     <p>SOme vſe wine for profit, ſome to make them merie withall, and ſome for pleaſure, and ſome for all theſe purpoſes. Wyne doth not only nouriſhe, but alſo maketh the meates to go wel downe, and ſtirreth vp the naturall heate and encreaſeth it. And the moſt part of them that vſe it ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlye, when as their bodie is withered before, they come into a good plight, and looke well. Wine hath this propertie, that it carieth and leadeth the meat vnto euerye ſmall part, and through ſtreyte wayes by the proper thinneſſe or ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his partes, &amp; it heateth the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers and ſmall parts, and maketh a good digeſtion, &amp; driueth forth water. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it fifteth forth the moſt part of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, but the greater power and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of wine may be ſpied more plainly in colde and withered bodies, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is leſſe naturall heat, as in olde men, and in ſuch as are amended of their ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But wine worketh not only theſe things which we haue ſpoken of before, in mens bodies, but alſo ſheweth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb facs="tcp:3182:31"/> chaungings wonderfully in a mans minde. For it maketh men merie, and to haue a good hope, to be manly and liberal, and many that we ſée before, cowardes, after the drinking of wine, to be made bolde, chearefull, of a good courage, and a good hope, and ſome that were niggards and filthy pinchers to be made liberall, and frée giuers. But wine if it be vſed out of meaſure, ouerthroweth and drowneth the liuely ſoundneſſe and ſtrength, and the naturall color, and it bringeth the hole palſie, the halfe palſie, the falling ſickneſſe, and the trembling of the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, it noyeth alſo the godlye and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall part of the ſoule, bicauſe they that gull in wine ſo, haue miſtie and darke ſenſes, and their minde is not cleare. Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto <hi>Simeon Sethi.</hi> Whyte ſmall wines that haue no great ſmell, are good for the ſinewes that are wounded. Wine is good to waſhe the moyſt fleſhe that is in olde ſores.<note place="margin">Some wines to be giuen in ſome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues at ſome times.</note> Wateriſh wine is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for them that haue the ague, and haue thin iuices therwith, &amp; it may be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in diuers agues, as <hi>Galen</hi> ſaith in his booke
<pb facs="tcp:3182:31"/> 
                        <hi>de methodo medendi,</hi> when as the rage of the ague is not great.<note place="margin">Wine good for the gout, occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</note> And althoughe wine when it is taken inwardly hurteth both the ſinewes and ioyntes, bicauſe it fumeth vp into the heade, and bréedeth rheumes which fall downe vnto them, yet for all that, if it be layde outwardlye vpon the ioyntes, it ſtrengthneth them, and maketh them faſt when as they are looſe by melting awaye or reſoluing the moyſture that is in them, and for that purpoſe ſerueth beſt of all other blacke wine, for the more that it is binding, the more it ſtrengthneth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Out of the boke of Galen which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth that the maners of the ſoule, and the complexion of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy follow one another.</head>
                     <p>WIne driueth away ſadneſſe, and penſiueneſſe, but it is ill if it be to largely taken. But if a man wil vſe it wiſely, it will digeſt, and diſtribute or conuey the nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, increaſe bloud &amp; noriſh, &amp; it wil alſo make the minde both gentler and bolder. <hi>Plato</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3182:32"/> in the .ij.<note place="margin">Plato de le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibus.</note> booke <hi>de legibus,</hi> forbiddeth all children wine y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are vnder .xij. houres old, for that inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhould not be driuen therwith into madneſſe, he ſuffreth them that are full growen in age, to vſe it, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a remedie againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of age, and driueth away ſorowes, &amp; ſwageth the hardneſſe of maners, the age of ſpringoldes or of growing children, is hote and full of muche bloude, contrary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the olde age is colde, and wanteth bloud, therefore the drinking of wine is profitable for olde men, but to them that are in growing, it is excéeding hurtfull, moreouer <hi>Plato</hi> did not ſuffer that the ſouldiers ſhoulde drinke any wine in the campe, neither bondmen in the citie, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther princes nor gouernors in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>welth, neither iudges, neither any other that ſhould enter in the counſell about a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny matter, bicauſe that wine as a certain tyrant doth rule &amp; ouercome the powers of the ſoule. Hitherto <hi>Galen.</hi> But bicauſe it hath bene diuerſe times ſayd, that wine is good for olde men, and it is not as yet fullye ſhewed what maner of wine that
<pb facs="tcp:3182:32"/> ſhould be, it ſhalbe beſt to teache men by <hi>Galen</hi> what wines are beſt for old men. <hi>Galen lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de ſanitate tuenda,</hi> ſayth: All your counſell muſt goe to this ende in choſing of wine fit for old men, that it may be very thin or ſubtil, in color rediſh yellow, or yellow, or pale yellow, which is of a middle color betwéene bright yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and white.<note place="margin">The war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in olde mens bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</note> There are two profites that come to old men by the vſe of wine, one is, that it warmeth all the members of their bodies, and the other is, that it ſcoureth out by the water all the whay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhneſſe or thin wateriſhnes of the bloud, and bicauſe it doth ſo effectuallye,<note place="margin">The ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring awaye of the whai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh watery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the bloud.</note> it is beſt for olde men. But ſuch wine is it that is thin in ſubſtance, &amp; driueth forth water, and is yellow in color, for that is the proper color of hote wines, and ſo alſo which haue bene from the beginning ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye white, and haue gotten a certaine yellowneſſe when they haue waxed old, wherevpon they begin firſt to be a little yellowiſhe pale, and afterwarde to be plainly yellow pale. But ſuch wines as are eyther pale yellow, or bright yellow,
<pb facs="tcp:3182:33"/> and a fat ſubſtaunce increaſe the bloud, &amp; nouriſh the bodie by reaſon wherof they are now &amp; then good for old men, to wete, at ſuch times whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they haue not much wheyiſh moiſture, &amp; would be more plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly noriſhed, but for all that, aged me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had more nede for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part, ſuch wines as make a man piſſe much, bicauſe they haue ſuch plenty of wateriſh excrements.</p>
                     <p>Now good reader ſéeing that almighty God our heauenly father hath giuen thée this noble creature of wine, ſo manye wayes profitable for our bodies and mindes, thanke him with all thy heart, not onely for it, but alſo for that he hath ſent learned Phiſitions to tell thée how, in what meaſure, and in what time thou ſhould vſe them, and not vſe them, and for what complexions and ages they are good, and for what complexions and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges they are euill. If thou take any harm by miſuſing this noble creature of God, blame not him, but thine owne ſelfe, that haſt abuſed it, contrary to his will, and to the learning of his officers &amp; ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants that taught thee the right vſe of it. Honor be giuen to God for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:33"/>
                  <p>This Booke ſheweth at large the powers, commodities, vertues, and properties of the three moſt renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and famous Preſeruatiues or Triacles: to weete, of the great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle called in Latine Theriaca Andro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machi: of the Triacle Salt: and of it that is called by the name of the firſt finder out and maker, Mithridatium: Gathered out of Galen and Aëtius, by the labours and paines of William Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, Doctor of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke.</p>
                  <p>Newly corrected and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</p>
                  <q>Mellis ſi nimia eſt copia, bilis erit.</q>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:34"/>
                  <head>William Turner to the <hi>gentle Reader.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>ORASMVCH AS</hi> both Chriſtian charity, and the common ciuil loue that euerye man oweth to his countrye, woulde and doth require that all Chriſtians and men liuing ciuilly togither in one common countrye, ſhoulde one helpe another with ſuch giftes, either of the minde, as learning, knowledge, wiſedome, and cunning, or with bodily giftes, as riches, ſtrength and all kinde of mans helpe, if they be more rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly repleniſhed therwith than their neighbors be: Methinke we that profeſſe the ſcience of Phiſick, and can ſhewe great helpe and comfort vnto our brethren and countrymen, as wel as men of other countries, to wete, Italians, Germanes, and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards haue done, might iustlye be accuſed of vnkindneſſe, if none of vs (being ſo many) would take in hand to declare in the Engliſh tong, the manifolde and worthie vertues of the great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle made by <hi>Andromachus:</hi> and of the Triacle <hi>Salt,</hi> which is called in Latine <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>theriacalis.</hi> Wherefore ſeeing that hitherto
<pb facs="tcp:3182:34"/> I haue not perceiued any man to haue taken that labour in hand, for the loue that I owe vnto al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God and his people, my countrymen of England, I will aduenture as well as I can, to declare the nature, vertue, propertie and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the forenamed Triacle, and alſo of the Triacle <hi>Salt.</hi> And bicauſe I am not minded to bring out any new thing of mine owne inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I entend for to gather the ſumme of this whole matter out of an olde Graecian, named <hi>Galen,</hi> the moſt famous writer of Phiſicke that wrote this .xiiij. hundred yeare in all Europa, Aſia, or Africa, and out of another famous Graecian named <hi>Aëtius,</hi> a man of great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: who gathered into a booke that is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode in Latin, all the most notable compoſitions that his predeceſſor (noble <hi>Galen</hi>) leſt behind him, and a great number of compoſitions of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines, written before <hi>Galens</hi> time by noble Phiſitions, wherof <hi>Galen</hi> made no mention: and alſo of no ſmall number of excellent compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions of medicines inuented by learned Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions after <hi>Galens</hi> time. If this my paine taken in this matter ſhall be perceiued to be thankefull vnto thee, and to be well taken, if God ſende me longer life and health, I will ſet ſomething more
<pb facs="tcp:3182:35"/> forth to the profite of all my country men, both my friendes and foes alſo. The maner of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the great Triacle, and Triacle <hi>Sale,</hi> and <hi>Mithridatium,</hi> maye be had both in Galen to Piſo, and alſo in Aetius. Wherefore if there be any Apothecaries of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, that dare take in hande to make theſe noble compoſitions, they may know now where to haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: or if that for lacke of ſome ſimple medicines, not eaſilye to he had in England, they dare not aduenture vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the making thereof: they maye haue them made alreadye from Venice, as faithfully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded at this time, as euer any Triacles haue bene made there theſe .xl. yeres. But now let vs reherſe the vertues and properties of theſe excellent medicines. And first of the great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3182:35"/>
                  <head>¶ Galen writeth to <hi>Piſo this.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE TRIACLE</hi> DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed by <hi>Andromachus</hi> the elder, is verye good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the biting of all wilde beaſtes and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes, againſt poyſoned medicines, againſt diſeaſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtomach, ſhortneſſe of winde, againſt the Colicke, againſt the iaundiſe, the dropſey, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of the lunges, all kinde of crampes or drawings togither, the pleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie, ſores of the bladder, ſtopping of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, paines of the kidneyes, peſtilent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and alſo the biting of a mad dog, if it be taken in the weight of the Beane of Egypt, with thrée ciathes of warme water: that is about the meaſure of foure ounces and a half. It is alſo good againſt the long during paines of the head, diſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the head, and hardneſſe of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: it mendeth the dulneſſe of the eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, it helpeth the falling ſickneſſe, and them that caſt out bloud, if a man will
<pb facs="tcp:3182:36"/> giue it with the broth of <hi>Comfrey.</hi> It draweth out the wormes in the guttes, it helpeth thoſe that haue diſeaſes of the liuer and milt, it helpeth thorowlye the bloudie flixe, and the common flixe that commeth of the ſlipperineſſe of the guts and ſtomacke, and the turning torments of the guts, eſpecially if the guttes haue no inflammation or great burning heate in them. Beſides this, when as the body waſteth away with to much ſweating, and his ſtrength is brought to weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; the nature of the diſeaſe will not ſuffer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of wine, this triacle dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ken, ſtayeth or ſtoppeth the ſweate, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoreth the ſtrength that was weakened before. It doth alſo prouoke downe to women their ſickeneſſe that hath bene long ſtopped, and it doth now and then open the ſtopping of the iſſue of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and of the Emrodes: for ſéeing that it is endued with ſundrye and mengled qualities or properties, therfore it ſprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding abrode ſomething &amp; making them thin, draweth them togither, that they maye be ſifted out. It vſeth for to ſtaye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:3182:36"/> things that flowe aboue meaſure, by reaſon of the weakneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of the body, or the power retentiue or hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding power, and therefore reſtoreth the ſtrength againe: and alſo it helpeth all diſeaſes of the ioyntes, when as the time of increaſing the diſeaſe is paſt, and it is come to the higheſt, for then thou ſhalte giue to drinke this triacle after thou haſt made fometations vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the aking place, the which in déede ſhall driue awaye the flowing humors that are ſtuffed in, and ſhall driue backe thoſe that woulde fall in afterwarde. This Triacle is good alſo for them that are of perfite health, if they take it oft. With the vſe of this Triacle, I haue oft times helped thoſe that haue the diſeaſe called in Greeke <hi>Elephantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis,</hi> and (now commonly called the lepre or leproſie, which is not in déede the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre of the olde Grecians, neither it that the ſcripture maketh mention of.) It is not onely good for the bodie, but alſo for the minde, for if it be oft drunken, it hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth melancholyke diſeaſes, and waſteth away blacke choler, by reaſon whereof
<pb facs="tcp:3182:37"/> it is alſo good for the Feuer Quartaine which commeth of blacke choler,<note place="margin">But it may not be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the beginning of a Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</note> other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe called melancholy. I haue deliuered many verie eaſily that haue bene ſicke of the Quartaine, with this remedie. For I vſe firſt to purge the ſick perſon by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting, which is done after meate, and the next daye I giue hym to drinke the iuice of wormwood, and then two houres before his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I geue him this Triacle, and oft times the pacient is by and by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from his fit. This medicine hath accuſtomably taken away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which of all diſeaſes is the worſt, and vſeth to come to a man after he is bitten of a mad dog. They that haue this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, are afrayde of water, and for the great dryneſſe that they haue within the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, they are deſirous of moyſture, but they forbeare or hold themſelues from drink, bicauſe that they are departed from their right minde and vnderſtanding, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not what woulde helpe them or doe them good. And therefore it commeth to paſſe that they flying &amp; eſchuing water, wither, and are drawen togither with a
<pb facs="tcp:3182:37"/> deadly crampe, by the reaſon of a hote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue that they are inwardly burnt with, and ſo at length die the wretchedſt kinde of death y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can be. I haue vſed ſomtimes to put ſome portion of this triacle meng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with roſe oyle, into the wounde that the madde dog hath made, that it might after the maner of a boxing glaſſe, ſucke and draw out from the bottome the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome, in ſo much that the Triacle is not onely good to be taken in, but alſo to be layde outwardly vpon the wound, which as ſoone as the dog hath made with his téeth, muſt be launced and cut rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and kept open, for the ſpace of foure dayes, that the venome may therby breth out, that the wounde be not ſtopped or growen vp againe. And for this purpoſe ye may make a cauteriſation in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wound to kepe it long open, but bicauſe the moſt part of men can better abide the akings than the burnings. If the wounde can be kept open with only cutting, it ſhall be better to let it abide ſo, in tender and weake perſons, but if it wil néedes grow to, then muſt it be kept open with bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:3182:38"/> or cauteriſation. A man cannot finde a better remedie than this triacle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the peſtilence, which being alſo as it were a wild beaſt, bred of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ayre, leaping vpon men by the inbreathing of that ill breaths which deſtroyeth, waſteth, and maketh hauock not only of one man, but of whole tounes and Cities.</p>
                  <p>And as <hi>Hipocrates</hi> draue away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence out of Athens w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great fires made of ſpice woods, and ſwéete floures, chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the temperature of the aire, that men by this meanes might draw in with their breath the purified or clenſed aire, for a remedye againſt the common euill that reigned there then: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle like a ſcouring or purging fire, will not ſuffer them that take it in before they be infected, to be infected at al: and deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them that are infected already, if they take it in afterward, chaunging the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious poyſon of the aire which they haue receyued by breath. And ſuffereth not the diſeaſe to ſpread any further. Wherfore I counſel thée, euen whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou art in thy
<pb facs="tcp:3182:38"/> beſt helth, to vſe oft this Triacle. But eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially when thou makeſt thy iorney in the winter. And this Triacle ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth alſo the wittes or ſenſes. It quicke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the minde or vnderſtanding, and ſo defendeth the body, by reaſon of the mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that it ſuffereth not the bodye to be ouercome by anye poyſon or venemous drink or potion. As it is reported of king <hi>Mithridates,</hi> who defended himſelfe ſo, not with the great triacle, which at that time was not, but with a preſeruatiue of his owne making, which after his owne name was called <hi>Mithridatium,</hi> that he could not be ouercommed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny poyſon, a man muſt vſe this Triacle after he hath perfitely digeſted. Somtime in the quantity of a beane of Egypt with thrée ounces &amp; a halfe of water. And ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time when he hath more time to digeſt the medicine, he may take the quantitie of a Haſel nut, with four ounces &amp; a halfe of water. But I would counſell no body to take this triacle in the heate of Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. Neyther ought it to be taken oft and much, of them that are of flouriſhing
<pb facs="tcp:3182:39"/> or luſty age, neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are of hote natures or complexions: I counſell alſo that they whoſe yeres turne towards age doe take it oft and much, not with water but with wine. Children in no caſe ought to receiue this medicine, bicauſe it will diſſolue or loſe in pieces their bodies. For I remember that I ſaw once a little boy, who by the vnſeaſonable vſing of thys Triacle, fell into a palſey.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Triacle Salt.</head>
                     <p>THe Triacle Salt is a medicinall Salt, made of diuers excellent herbes, and of burnt Salt and burnt Vipers, or elſe of the tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſkes of Vipers being burnt. And the compoſition of this Salt, is found both in <hi>Galen</hi> and alſo in <hi>Aëtius. Galen</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth thus of the triacle Salt: not word for word but in ſentence, as I am ready for to proue, if any man holde the contrarye. The triacle Salt (ſaith <hi>Galen</hi>) is good for the ſame diſeaſes, poiſons, bitings and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things that the great Triacle is good
<pb facs="tcp:3182:39"/> for, but it worketh not ſo effectuouſly nor in ſo ſhort a time. Some peraduenture will thinke that the vertue of Triacle Salt ſhall ſoone vaniſhe awaye, bicauſe the Vipers which are the principall grounde of the medicine are burned, and thereby léefe their ſtrength: but that is not true, for manye things by reaſon of the fire are made better, or elſe declare their nature that lurketh. We melt or trie golde by the fire, and it that is coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit golde, is bewrayed thereby, and it that is good golde, is declared to be good, by the triall of the fire. And iron alſo is made ſoft by the fire and bowable, and ſo is made fit for many things neceſſary for mans life. Are not alſo manye things that we receyue inwardly for the noriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our bodies made better by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> help of the fire?</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Galen</hi> rehearſeth examples of diuerſe other things which are made better by burning of them in the fire. And ſo hée ſayth, that al Vipers burnt whole, do put away their poyſon that they had before, &amp; are made holſome by the fire. Although
<pb facs="tcp:3182:40"/> the triacle Salt be good for manye other things, yet properly and eſpecially it hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth thoſe diſeaſes that riſe in the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt part of the ſkin: as the ſcuruye e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill that goeth through the ſkin into the fleſh, and maketh it of a white colour, the common lepre of the Grecians and ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and the Wild ſcabby or ſcuruy euil. And it driueth awaye lice that bréede of corruption, and beſides theſe, it ſcoureth the téeth verye well, and ſuffereth them not to be eaten thorow, and it ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the gummes that are loſe, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth downe or ſtoppeth the flowing and the rotting of them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Of the Triacle Salt: out of Aëtius.</head>
                     <p>THe Triacle Salt is good for all things that the great Triacle is after a moderate maner, and ſheweth his profite by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vſing of it: howbeit there are ſome that denie vtterly that it hath any power to helpe or doe any good, alledging that
<pb facs="tcp:3182:40"/> the propertie of the Vipers is deſtroyed by the burning, but I dare affirme that although the Triacle Salt hath not ſo great vertues as the great Triacle hath: Yet neuertheleſſe that it léeſeth not his ſtrength by the comming into the fier. For there are manye things which are found and perceyued to be better for that they haue bene in the fier, as golde, lime, and ſuch like. For Vipers burnt whole in the fier, put awaye by the reaſon of the fier, their more ſtrong and hurfull propertie, and take of the fire their hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome temperature and right propertie. The Triacle Salt is chieflye commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in helping the diſeaſes of the ſkin, as the white Morphew, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lepre of the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, and Scripture, the wilde ſcurfe, and the ſickenſſe nowe commonlye cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Lepre, which in déede is not the Lepre, but <hi>Elephantiaſis,</hi> the blacke morphew, wilde ſcabbes, thinneſſe and falling of the heare, for it doth awaye by and by ſuch euilles or griefes of the ſkin and driueth awaye verye well ſharp ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements, being in plenty vnder the ſkin.
<pb facs="tcp:3182:41"/> The vſe of this Salt driueth out ſweate of many, and ſo by the ſweating, the rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſubſtance is emptied out: in ſo much that certaine drawe out lice in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, within .14. dayes after the vſe of this medicine at the moſt, &amp; afterwardes there appeared no more anye lice, but ſome in ſtede of lice, caſt out flemmy ſpit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, beginning firſt with the caſting out of the Salt: and then within a little while after, when the ſpittell is purged out, it is ſtopped. Ye maye vſe it as well at dinner, as at ſupper, with what ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer kinde of meate ye liſt to take it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall ye néede to prouoke anye man further, to the receiuing of it. For there is ſuch pleaſauntneſſe in it, that a man might ſaye, it were rather made for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, than for other intentes. A man may take the quantitie of three ſpoonefuls in one daye, eſpecially if the meate be well digeſted in the ſtomach before. They that eate it haue a better digeſtion, and a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter appetite to their meate, and they haue a more floriſhing or luſtie body, and all their wittes or ſenſes luſtier and freſher.
<pb facs="tcp:3182:41"/> It diſſolues ſuffuſions that are yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, and not fully growen togither. Neyther ſhall any man be in daunger of ſuffuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that vſeth them dayly. The ſame prouoketh the monethlye diſeaſe of wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that are ſtopped by reaſon of a clu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering or ſtopping co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geling of the bloud, the ſame ſtayeth and ſtoppeth the outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious and large flowing of the ſame. Whoſoeuer will take it afore hand, ſhall ouercome all the lying in waite of beaſts that caſt out poyſon, neither when a man is hurt with the venome alreadye, &amp; take the Salt by and by after, ſhall run into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daunger thereby, eſpecially if he haue prepared, or as it were ſeaſoned the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexion of his body a long time before, by the vſing of this Salt. It is good to flie for ſuccour vnto this helping medicine, which driueth away the euill in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Peſtilence, eſpeciallye if thou menge withall ſome part of <hi>Tama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſke.</hi> Furthermore the triacle Salt is good phiſicke for the moſt part of all diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, and eſpecially for ſuch as are in the kidneyes, for it breaketh the ſtones that
<pb facs="tcp:3182:42"/> are in them,<note place="margin">Suffuſion is the running of a noiſome humor in the eye which if it be not ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth haw and pearle in the eye, and ſome name this diſeaſe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taracta.</note> and when they are ſore wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened, reſtoreth and maketh them freſhe againe. There can no like medicine be giuen, to helpe the diſineſſe of the head, &amp; headaches, and to the falling ſickeneſſe, vnto this if a man will take it plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlye, for the ſpace of a yeare, I haue knowen olde iaundiſes, and thoſe that haue hadde yll miltes, and men diſeaſed with the Colike, which fell oft into that diſeaſe, to haue bene holpen by this Salt. And I haue dried vp the dropſey with it, eſpecially it that goeth betwene the fell and the fleſhe. And I haue driuen away the diſeaſe of vnſatiable hunger, which is called in greke <hi>Bulimos,</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſalt: &amp; alſo if it be eaten, it helpeth thoſe that go in colde ayre, that they take no harme therby. It ſtayeth continuall quiuerings or ſhaking, that come to one by courſes, and drieth vp moyſt horce and coughes. This Salt ſpinkled vppon the meate bringeth them that were conſumed with a conſumption, to their right ſtate again, and maketh them that are loſed by weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to amende agayne. For I knowe
<pb facs="tcp:3182:42"/> manye that haue had all their members loſed, that is to ſaye ſtricken with a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey, reſtored to their perfite helth againe. This etable Salt a man woulde thinke that it were onely made for them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to haue the goute, and for all them that haue anye diſeaſe of the ioyntes, it helpeth them ſo ſpedilye. A man can not well expreſſe howe much this Salt will ſtaye and hinder olde quarteyns, and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings or madneſſe, that ryſe of melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, if it be taken before the fittes, or in the ſpace betwene the fittes, it killeth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo all kinde of wormes, it is alſo verye good to rub the téeth, ſpeciallye the great téeth, for it doth make the téeth not onely the whiter, but alſo ſtrengthneth them, ſo that no tooth ſhal mooue or be loſed after, nor eaten thorow, nor ſet on edge.</p>
                     <p>It draweth alſo out of the head y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great plenty of humors, &amp; purgeth it and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the eies lighter. The phiſition muſt occupie this triacle Salt after diuers ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and wayes: as for an example. If he will giue this Salt to one that ſpitteth bloud, let him put the ſixt part of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3182:43"/> bruſed and ſifted, to one proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or quantitie of this Salt: as to fiue ſpoonefuls of the Salt, one of <hi>Comfrey.</hi> In the curing of them that are ſick in the conſumption of the lungs, called the pti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and them that haue matter running out of their breaſts: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> phiſition muſt put alſo to one part of the Salt, ſixe parts of Oris pouder, or Dittamy of Candy. To the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are diſeaſed in the liuer, Ground pine, to them that are diſeaſed in the milt, the roote of Swines bread, called <hi>Cyclamem,</hi> or the barkes of Capers, or put vnto the ſixt part of pepper. If thou wilt dreſſe it for them that haue the gout, take awaye the halfe of the preſcribed weight of Satirion, taking good héede that thou ſtirreſt not vp furious plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, &amp; ſuch as loſe the ioynts in them. But the Salt will breake the ſtone in the kidneys, moſt of all if it haue mixed with it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruit of <hi>Balſamum</hi> or Gru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mell ſede. If thou wilt make a ſtronger power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt poiſons, thou ſhalt double y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of <hi>Scordiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> otherwiſe called Water Germaunder, and Horehound, in the
<pb facs="tcp:3182:43"/> making of the Salt: and beſide that, thou ſhalt adde dried Duckes bloud. It will be better for them that are bitten of a mad dog, if they put vnto it the rootes of Piony or burnt Crabbes. The Salt wil be good for them that haue their neckes growen backwarde, by reaſon of draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing togither of the ſinewes, if they can abide to haue a litle <hi>Caſtoreum,</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>popanax,</hi> mixed with it. It cleareth and maketh ſharp the eye ſight, if thou put in thy Salt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaues of <hi>Malabathrum,</hi> in double quantitie. It helpeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> digeſtions of meate, if there be put in it a ſufficient quantitie of <hi>Caſſia,</hi> and <hi>Coſtus,</hi> for the ſwelling that commeth of winde. Put Commin to it, it will prouoke brine or water in greater plentie, if thou put of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſéede of <hi>Dancus</hi> to it. It will deliuer a man ſooner from the quartein if right vp growing Veruin and Agrimonie, and the iuice of <hi>Cireneik</hi> or Laſer it ſelfe be mixed with it. But to tell the ſumme of the matter ſhortlye. Whatſoeuer thou knoweſt to be holeſome and good for the diſeaſed member, mixe that with the
<pb facs="tcp:3182:44"/> Salt: either in the making of it, or in the quantitie that thou entendeſt to giue in. But we muſt not giue it to them that are with childe, nor to ſucking children, neither to other little children, neyther to them that are of a hoter complexion, and eſpecially not in Summer, neyther to them that haue a ſharpe and a drie ague in any caſe. Hitherto haue I written of the great Triacle and the Triacle Salt: but bicauſe there are manye excellent vertues, helpes, and remedies that may be had alſo of the noble preſeruatiue me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine called <hi>Mithridatium,</hi> bearing the name of <hi>Mithridates</hi> the king, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented it, I thinke I ſhall doe well alſo to declare to ſuch as vnderſtande no La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, the vertues, properties, remedies, and helpes, that maye be had of that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatiue: which maye be taken with much leſſe ieoperdie, then the great Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acle can be taken. Yea maye take at the moſt, the quantitie of a haſell nut of this medicine. They that are come to full age may take the qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>titie of a beane of <hi>Grae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia,</hi> which is called <hi>Lotos.</hi> This quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie
<pb facs="tcp:3182:44"/> may be encreaſed or diminiſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middle ages, and they that haue no ague maye take it with wine, or with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied wine, or ſugared wine, or with ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced wine, if that they haue a ſtopped li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. But they that are agewiſh, muſte take it with water, or Mede. It is verie good for old reumes that flow downe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtomach and breſt, and for all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtumes, and deepe old exulcerations or wearing of the ſkin that are far and depe in the bodye. It is good for them that are in a conſumption, and them that haue great plentie of winde in their bellies, and it helpeth the common flix, it men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the dull appetite, and bringeth a freſhe appetite againe. And maketh a mans body haue a good color, it breaketh the ſtone, it helpeth them that cannot but with great paine make water, and ſuffereth not melancholy to be gathered togither. It ſharpeneth their ſight that receiue it, if it be taken afore hande, it hath a great power to hinder or let that a man be not hurt with any kinde of dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye poyſon, for the which cauſe it was
<pb facs="tcp:3182:45"/> firſt ordeyned and inuented of King <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridates.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>AN ADMONITION OF William Turner to the Reader.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough both <hi>Galen</hi> and <hi>Aëtius</hi> hath giuen ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent warning vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; women, at what times, in what ages, complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in what diſeaſes theſe medicines maye be hurtfull or hole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome to the receyuers of it: yet marking the great dull groſſeneſſe of many Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh men that cannot vnderſtand it, that is plainly ſpoken, and the fooliſh hardy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of other ſome that care not for ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient warning, but will boldlye become murtherers of themſelues, by miſuſing of Gods creatures, not vſing them by the aduiſe of almightie Gods ſeruauntes and officers the learned Phiſitions, but out of time, and out of meaſure take them in, without al diſcretion, folowing
<pb facs="tcp:3182:45"/> onelye their owne aduiſe or els the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of ſome doting olde Gooddame, or ſome craking Cremer, or prating runna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Pedlar, I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not think my ſelf ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly diſcharged, except I giue warning to all men and women that wil vſe theſe medicines, that they take the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not in raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnaduiſedly, without the aduiſe and counſell of a learned phiſition, who may tell them, whether they be agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for their natures and complexions and diſeaſes or no. The which thing if they will not doe, neither will learne in what quantitie they ought to be taken, neither what perſons, of what ages, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at what times they ought to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, doubtleſſe, I thinke that it will chaunce ſometime, that the moſt preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous medicines ſhall turne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their owne deſtructions. Let no man now ſay but he is ſufficiently warned. The great Tria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle &amp; the <hi>Mithridatium</hi> may be had wel, euen of the beſt making, of the moſt part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apothecaries of the citie of London: and ſometimes of other that trauaile to Venice, all theſe three ſortes are nowe
<pb facs="tcp:3182:46"/> lately made and dreſſed in the famous Citie of Venice.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>THE NAMES OF DIS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes and griefes that maye be healed by the great Triacle, called <hi>Theria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca Andromachi,</hi> as Galen wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his booke vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Piſo.</head>
                     <list>
                        <item>THE biting of all venemous beaſts and ſerpents.</item>
                        <item>All kinde of poyſons and poyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned drinkes.</item>
                        <item>The diſeaſes of the ſtomach.</item>
                        <item>Shortneſſe of winde.</item>
                        <item>The Colicke.</item>
                        <item>The Iaundiſe or Gucleſought.</item>
                        <item>The Dropſey.</item>
                        <item>The conſumption of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lungs or ptiſick.</item>
                        <item>All kinde of Cramps, or drawings togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or ſhrinking of ſinewes.</item>
                        <item>The pleureſey or ſide ague with a ſtitch, and ſpitting of bloud, and vlcerations.</item>
                        <item>Sores of the bladder.</item>
                        <item>Stopping of water or vrine.</item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3182:46"/>
                        <item>Paines of the Kidneyes.</item>
                        <item>Peſtilence, and peſtilent diſeaſes.</item>
                        <item>The biting of a mad dog.</item>
                        <item>Olde headakes.</item>
                        <item>Diſineſſe of the head.</item>
                        <item>Hardneſſe of hearing.</item>
                        <item>The dulneſſe of the eye ſight.</item>
                        <item>The falling ſickneſſe.</item>
                        <item>Vomiting of bloud.</item>
                        <item>Wormes in the guttes.</item>
                        <item>The diſeaſes of the Liuer.</item>
                        <item>The diſeaſes of the Milt.</item>
                        <item>The bloudie flix.</item>
                        <item>The common flix.</item>
                        <item>The turning tormentes of the guttes.</item>
                        <item>Waſting away with to much ſweating.</item>
                        <item>The ſtopping of womens monthly ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</item>
                        <item>The ſtopping of the mother.</item>
                        <item>The ſtopping of the Emrodes.</item>
                        <item>All ſuperfluous flowings of the body.</item>
                        <item>All diſeaſes of the ioyntes.</item>
                        <item>Poyſoning, and falling to perillous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</item>
                        <item>The common Lepre called <hi>Elephantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3182:47"/>
                        <item>The diſeaſe of the minde that came of melancholye.</item>
                        <item>All melancholicke diſeaſes.</item>
                        <item>Plentie of choler: called melancholy.</item>
                        <item>The quartaine ague.</item>
                        <item>The feare of water after the biting of a mad dog:</item>
                        <item>The weakeneſſe of the wittes or ſenſes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>THE NAMES OF THE diſeaſes and griefes that maye be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Triacle Salt: according vnto the learning of Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len and Aëtius.</head>
                     <p>All the diſeaſes of the ſkin, but chiefly theſe that follow.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>THe white Morphew.</item>
                        <item>The Lepre of the Grecians and ſcripture.</item>
                        <item>The wilde ſcurfe.</item>
                        <item>The common Lepre, called in Latin <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephantiaſis.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>The blacke morphew.</item>
                        <item>Wilde ſcabbes.</item>
                        <item>The falling of the heare.</item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3182:47"/>
                        <item>Thinneſſe of the heares.</item>
                        <item>Stopping of ſweate.</item>
                        <item>Ouermuch plentie of flegmaticke excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</item>
                        <item>Lacke of digeſtion.</item>
                        <item>Lacke of appetite.</item>
                        <item>Dulneſſe of ſenſes or wittes.</item>
                        <item>Suffuſions that bréede the hawe, and pearle in the eye, called of ſome <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racta.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Stopping of venemous diſeaſes.</item>
                        <item>The outragious flowing of venemous diſeaſes.</item>
                        <item>The bitting of venemous beaſts and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentes.</item>
                        <item>The peſtilence and contagious aire.</item>
                        <item>The diſeaſe of the kidneyes.</item>
                        <item>The debilitie and weakeneſſe of the kid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys.</item>
                        <item>Olde headaches.</item>
                        <item>The falling ſickneſſe.</item>
                        <item>Olde Iaundiſe.</item>
                        <item>The diſeaſes of the Milt.</item>
                        <item>The Colicke.</item>
                        <item>The dropſey.</item>
                        <item>The vnſatiable hunger called <hi>Bulimos.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3182:48"/>
                        <item>The cold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> taketh in cold weather.</item>
                        <item>Shakings and tremblings, that come before agues.</item>
                        <item>Conſumptions, Ptiſicks, and waſtings of the bodye.</item>
                        <item>The Palſie and weakneſſe of the ioints, and other members.</item>
                        <item>The Goute.</item>
                        <item>All diſeaſes of the ioyntes.</item>
                        <item>Olde quartaines.</item>
                        <item>Dotings, and madneſſe that come of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholie.</item>
                        <item>All kinde of wormes that breede within a man.</item>
                        <item>The rotting &amp; other diſeaſes of the téeth.</item>
                        <item>Rheumaticke humors in the head.</item>
                        <item>Certaine diſeaſes of the eyes.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>THE NAMES OF THE diſeaſes that may be healed by the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble preſeruatiue medicine called <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thridatium,</hi> as Galen and Aëtius and all other learned Phiſitions, that wrote after them of ſuch matter, do beare witneſſe in their writings.</head>
                     <list>
                        <pb facs="tcp:3182:48"/>
                        <item>THe ſtopping of the Liuer.</item>
                        <item>Olde reumes flowing downe into the ſtomacke and breſt.</item>
                        <item>Impoſtumes.</item>
                        <item>Déepe vlcerations, and of ſcraping of the ſkin that are farre in the body.</item>
                        <item>Conſumptions and Ptiſicks.</item>
                        <item>Windyneſſe in the body.</item>
                        <item>The common flixe.</item>
                        <item>The dull appetite.</item>
                        <item>Euill fauored color of the face and other places of the body.</item>
                        <item>The ſtone.</item>
                        <item>Hardneſſe and painefulneſſe in making of water.</item>
                        <item>Gathering togither of melancholy.</item>
                        <item>Dulneſſe of the eye ſight.</item>
                        <item>All deadly poyſon.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="colophon">
                  <p>¶ Imprinted at London by <hi>William Seres, dwelling at the</hi> West ende of Paules, at the ſigne of the Hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bogge.</p>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
